Finding Aid for Ellis B. Merry papers, 1907-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ellis B. Merry papers 1907-1989
Merry, Ellis B., 1907-1989.
0271 Aa 2; Ac
Senior and executive vice president of the National Bank of Detroit, later chairman of the board. The collection concerns business activities, personal interests, and travels. Included are business and personal correspondence, journals, travel materials, and other materials relating in part to his interest in amateur radio.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
2 linear feet
1 oversize folders
The collection was donated by the Merry family (donor no. 8970 ) in 2001
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Ellis Boyd Merry, the son of Earl D. Merry (1882-September 1957) and Lillian (Eck) Merry, was born in Kalamazoo, MI on January 30, 1907. Having moved with his family to Pontiac, MI soon after his birth, he attended school in that city with two brothers, William James and Henry A. and one sister, Katherine. By 1931, Ellis Merry had received a bachelor of arts followed by a law degree from the University of Michigan. Upon graduation, he immediately joined the Detroit law firm of Buckley, Ledyard, Dickinson & Wright, which had among its clients the National Bank of Detroit. In 1937, he took a leave of absence from the law firm to serve as an Assistant District Attorney in the Michigan State Banking Department under Charles T. Fisher. In 1944, having decided to shift from law to finance, he became a Vice President in the Loaning Division of National Bank of Detroit. He served as the Bank's Senior Vice President from 1958 to 1964, as its Executive Vice President from 1964 to 1968, as its Executive Committee Chairman from 1968 to 1969 and as its Board of Directors Chairman from January 1, 1970 to February 1, 1972. During his tenure, Merry significantly expanded the National Bank's global involvement and traveled extensively on international business.
Though retiring in 1972, Merry continued to serve as a National Bank of Detroit Director until 1979. Throughout his career, he also held directorships with companies such as McLouth Steel, the Ambassador Bridge Corporation, Grand Trunk Western Railroad, the Detroit Branch of the Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago and the Western American Bank of London, England. After his retirement, he remained on the boards of several companies including Douglas & Lomason and Sheller-Globe into the mid-1980s.
On October 2, 1937, Merry wed a Canadian from Toronto, Lorraine Armstrong (1915-1955). She was the daughter of Mr. and Mrs. Bryon M. Armstrong and had one brother, Frank L. Armstrong. The Merrys eventually settled in Grosse Pointe, MI. where they were active in Grosse Pointe Memorial Presbyterian Church. Following his wife's demise in late October 1955 after a long illness, Merry, on December 7, 1956, married Grosse Pointer Mrs. Elizabeth (Austin) Whitehead (1904-1981), whose first husband was Thomas Cram Whitehead (1893-1954). The couple continued to live in Grosse Pointe Farms. The new Mrs. Merry was active in community organizations such as the Junior League of Detroit and often accompanied her husband on his many business trips. An interest in amateur radio begun as a teenager became a primary interest of Merry as an adult, especially after leaving the National Bank. Two years after his second wife's death on September 23, 1981, Merry, on April 16, 1983, wed Martha Jean (Miller) Dodenhoff (8/28/1909-10/21/1999) whose first husband was Dr. Charles F. Dodenhoff (12/21/1907-8/30/1974). With his new bride, Merry continued to live in Grosse Pointe Farms, and the couple traveled frequently until his death on July 3, 1988.
The Ellis B. Merry Personal Papers were assembled by Merry during his lifetime and include a number of documents from his years spent at the National Bank of Detroit. The collection, as arranged by his stepdaughter, Jean Dodenhoff, focuses primarily on his business activities, personal interests and travels. Materials found here include business and personal correspondence, journals, lists, some legal documents and publications, commendation certificates, travel itineraries, chronologies, reports, and memorabilia. There are a significant number of photographs documenting the boards of directors on which he served as well as the bank-related activities in which he participated. The collection has been arranged into the following series: Business Activities; Personal Activities; Personal Journals; Travel; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Merry, Ellis B., 1907-1989.; Amateur radio stations--Michigan.; Bankers--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Commerce.; National Bank of Detroit.; Travelers.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Merry, Ellis B., 1907-1989.; Banks--Michigan.; National Bank of Detroit.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Business Activities 1933-1980s
  Series I. Business Activities 1933-1980s. This series is primarily concerned with Merry's business activities after he joined the National Bank of Detroit in 1944. This series contains documents, reports, publications and memorabilia pertaining to the bank as well as similar materials concerning his other business activities including his directorships for companies such as McLouth Steel from 1956 to 1971, the Ambassador Bridge Corporation and the Grand Trunk Western Railroad from 1966 to 1987(?).
  - National Bank of Detroit 1933-1972
    The National Bank of Detroit subseries covers business activities related to Merry's various positions with National Bank as well as his extra-curricular participation in annual staff skits and in the Officers Revolver Club of the National Bank of Detroit. Correspondence, memos, programs and reports are found here. Of special interest are Merry's 1955 report on the deposit structure of Detroit banks and his 1972 Retirement Tribute from the National Bank Board.
    - 1954, 1964-1971 (Box 1)
    - Historical Background 1933-1968 1960s (Box 1)
    - Merry, Ellis B. 'Deposit Structure ... Detroit Banks 1945-1954 and Business Development Program," March 22, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Extra-Curricular Activities 1950s-1960s (Box 1)
    - Personal Correspondence mid 1960s-early 1970s (Box 1)
    - Retirement-Board of Directors Tribute January 10, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Other Corporations / Organizations 1960s-1980s
    The Other Corporations and Organizations subseries covers Merry's activities with organizations other than the National Bank of Detroit. Not only is there material pertaining to directorships worldwide such as Douglas & Lomason Company (1958-1986), the Federal Reserve System, Grand Trunk Western Railroad Corporation, Investment and Merchant Finance Corporation, McLouth Steel Corporation and Western American Bank(Europe) Ltd., there are also documents related to organizations such as the Adela Investment Company, the Detroit Bar Association and the Overseas Bankers Club. Most extensive are items pertaining to his participation with the Sheller-Globe Board of Directors (1966-1986). Included in the subseries are correspondence, invitations, lists of participants, meeting minutes and reports.
    - Corporate Directorships 1960s-1980s (Box 1)
    - Corporate Directorships-Sheller Globe Corporation 1970s-1980s (Box 1)
    - Other Organization Participation late 1960s-early 1970s (Box 1)
- Personal Activities 1921-1988
  Series II. Personal Activities 1921-1988. Documents relating to Merry's personal life are found in this series. Merry and his first wife, Loraine Armstrong, had no children, but there is some material relating to her family. Also of interest are documents pertaining to his brother, Henry, a respected political scientist and university professor. Items about his amateur radio activities, friends, the family's Harbor Beach summer cottage, club memberships and personal gifts predominate. Included are letters, legal documents, correspondence, lists, and invitations.
  - Amateur Radio 1921-1988
    The largest subseries, Amateur Radio, includes information relating to Merry's amateur radio activities is also among the earliest. In addition to membership certificates beginning in 1921, there are numerous citations for worldwide contacts which he made over the years. There are several documents and articles concerning the legalities of radio antenna installation as well as a license plate with his call sign, plaques for the 1977 and 1978 American Radio Relay League and 1973 Challenger tapes.
    - Activities 1921-1923, 1973-1988 (Box 1)
    - Antenna (including legalities) 1960s-1970s (Box 1)
    - Bicentennial Car License Plate with Call Sign 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Challenger Tapes, March 4, 1973 and Lapel Pins (Box 1)
    - Licenses (Folder 1)
    - Plaque-American Radio Relay League December 20, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Plaque-American Radio Relay League June 27, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    Letters and related correspondence in the Correspondence subseries are primarily from friends made in law school or on Merry's many travels. There are also materials relating to the family summer cottage at Harbor Beach, MI, club memberships, party invitations and gifts ordered for friends or personal use. Of special interest are his 1974 purchase of a Liberty Bell reproduction (now at the St. Clair Shores Public Library) and his contributions to community organizations such as the NAACP and Henry Ford Hospital.
    - 1956-1987 (Box 1)
    - Purchases and Gifts 1964-1988 (Box 1)
  - Family 1930-1980s
    Much of the Family subseries concerns Merry's first wife, Lorraine, and her family. There is also information about his younger, political scientist brother, Henry, as well as his sister, Katherine. Legal documents relating to his purchase of a home on Lothrop Road in Grosse Pointe Farms are found here. That home was sold when he married Martha Jean Dodenhoff. The subseries contains correspondence, various legal documents, clippings, lists, and notes. Especially interesting is the planning done by Merry for his 80th birthday party.
    - Correspondence and Legal Documents 1930-1987 (Box 1)
    - Merry, Henry J,. 1960s, 1980s (Box 1)
    - Homes 1950s-1960s (Box 1)
  - Personal Documents
    The Personal Papers subseries contains miscellaneous materials acquired by Merry from his college into his retirement years. There are numerous certificates and commendations ranging from those admitting him to the Bar to those issued upon his retirement from directorships and his passage across the Equator. Several publications are found here including several law briefs and a "Michigan Law Review" with an article by Merry. Taking place on July 8, 1988 at Grosse Pointe Memorial Presbyterian Church, Merry's memorial service is documented as are contributions in his name and a formal tribute from the National Bank of Detroit Board.
    - Certificates and Commendations 1973, 1980s (Box 1)
    - Diplomas (Folder 1)
    - Education-Law Briefs 1920s-1930s (Box 1)
    - Education-Michigan Law Review December 1933 (Box 1)
    - Passports 1967-1988 (Box 1)
    - Memorial Service and Related Documents July 1988 (Box 1)
    - Memorial Tribute-National Bank of Detroit Board of Directors July 15, 1988 (Box 1)
- Personal Journals
  Series III. Personal Journals 1953-1988. While at National Bank of Detroit as well as during his retirement, Merry kept handwritten calendars and journals of his activities. Some including those of pocket size documented his day-to-day activities while others in book form covered his frequent travels. While not all years or trips are represented, there is documentation of travels to much of Europe, Australia and China.
  - Pocket diaries, 1968-1988
    The pocket-size diaries have one month per page. They contains brief notes of Merry's important appointments and activities especially with regard to his business and retirement endeavors. There is a complete set of these journals from 1968 to 1988 except for 1986.
    - 1968-1973 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1988 (Box 2)
  - Travel journals 1953-1986
    Frequently when he traveled, Merry kept a daily handwritten journal in which he recorded his activities and impressions. Not all years or trips are covered, and after 1972, there is less emphasis on business enterprises and more on sightseeing. Among the regions of the world visited by Merry were most countries of Europe, the Near East, Australia, South America, North Africa and China.
    - 1953-1956 (Box 2)
    - 1958, 1960 (Box 2)
    - 1962, 1963 (Box 2)
    - 1965, 1967 (Box 2)
    - 1970, 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1986 (Box 2)
- Travel 1950s-1987
  Series IV. Travel 1950s-1987. This series contains documentation of Merry's many travels for both business and pleasure. His earlier trips appear to have been planned by either National Bank of Detroit staff or by Merry personally. Later journeys were apt to be taken with clubs such as the English Speaking Union and the Circumnavigators or with tour groups such as INTRAV. Included are reservation correspondence, itineraries, maps, participant lists, business notes and memorabilia. Of interest are chronologies of various trips from 1953 through 1985 prepared by Merry.
  - Business related 1950s-1984
    The materials in this subseries relate primarily to Merry's business activities. Mrs. Elizabeth Merry accompanied her husband on some of these trips. Until 1972, these journeys was usually connected to the National Bank of Detroit ventures. Correspondence, itineraries, maps, some participant lists, business notes and memorabilia are found here. The chronologies prepared by Merry are of especial interest as is a clipping of a 1962 Detroit Board of Commerce Around the World Tour in which Merry participated.
    - Chronologies 1953-1984 (Box 2)
    - 1950s (Box 2)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Personal 1962-1987
    In addition to his business trips, Merry took a number of excursions either by himself or with his wife. After retiring though continued to plan some trips, he often joined with organizations' such as the English Speaking Union (ESU) or the Circumnavigators. He took several boat trips with the Royal Viking Line and turned to tour groups such as INTRAV for tours to more "exotic" regions such as the Orinoco River. This subseries includes correspondence, itineraries, participant lists and memorabilia.
    - With Elizabeth Merry 1962-1979 (Box 2)
    - Australian Tour (including a Commentary by Ellis B. Merry) 1981-1982 (Box 2)
    - With Martha Jean Merry 1982-1987 (Box 2)
- Photographs
  Series V. Photographs. Merry collected photographs relating to both his business and personal activities. Those from his time at National Bank of Detroit include both formal Board of Directors portraits and informal staff activity depictions. Of interest are pictures which record important bank business endeavors. There are also group portraits of various other boards of directors on which he served. If known, those pictured have been identified. In addition to his travels, his immediate family and his hobbies are depicted here as well.
  - Merry, Ellis B. Portraits (esp. business) 1950s-1970s (Box 2)
  - National Bank of Detroit Board Members-Group Portraits 1960s-1980s (Box 2)
  - National Bank of Detroit-Related Activities 1950s-1970s (Box 2)
  - National Bank of Detroit-Travel 1950s-1970s (Box 2)
  - Participation on Other Boards-Group Portraits 1970s-1980s (Box 2)
  - Personal Activities & Family 1934, 1962-1982 (Box 2)
  - Michigamua-Tribe of 1928 (Folder 1)
  - Ellis Merry Portrait 1970s (Folder 1)
  - National Detroit Corporation Board of Directors 12/9/1974 (Folder 1)